Finding Aid for the Akira Fujita Papers LSC.0296
UCLA Library Special Collections
Akira Fujita papers
1946-1992
UCLA Library Special Collections
Fujita, Akira
LSC.0296
64.0 Linear Feet (32 boxes)
Fujita was born February 17, 1920 in Brawley, California. In 1922 he was taken to Miho in the city of Shimizu, Japan, where he was raised by his maternal grandparents. He attended Waseda University from 1937-40. He returned to California and farmed with his father in the Imperial Valley before the outbreak of World War II. Fujita was sent to internment camps at Poston, Arizona; Tule Lake, California; and Crystal City, Texas. While at Tule Lake, he edited a literary journal, Doto, and contributed to another, Tessaku. In 1945 he renounced his American citizenship under duress, and did not regain his citizenship until 1957. A Kibei-Nisei writer, he became a central figure in the literary society Nanka Bungei and of the literary journal of the same name. He also wrote the first two novels of a projected trilogy: Nochi no kokei (An Agricultural Landscape, 1982) and Tachinoki no kisetsu (An Evacuation Season, 1984). The collection consists of diaries, manuscripts, drafts, galleys, incoming correspondence files, personal memorabilia, copies of Akira Fujita's published writings, and books by Nanka Bungei writers and others. Most of the collection is in Japanese.
32 boxes (16 linear ft.)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Grace Yaeno Fujita, 1995.
General note
[characters] indicates Japanese characters included in the print version of this online finding aid, available for consultation at the UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections.
General note
[characters] indicates Japanese characters included in the print version of this online finding aid, available for consultation at the UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942330503606533
Biography
Fujita was born February 17, 1920 in Brawley, California; in 1922 he was taken to Miho in the city of Shimizu, Japan, where he was raised by his maternal grandparents; attended Waseda University, 1937-40; returned to California and farmed with his father in the Imperial Valley before the outbreak of World War II; Fujita was sent to internment camps at Poston, Arizona, Tule Lake, California, and Crystal City, Texas; while at Tule Lake, he edited a literary journal, Doto, and contributed to another, Tessaku; in 1945 he renounced his American citizenship under duress, and did not regain his citizenship until 1957; a Kibei-Nisei writer, he became a central figure in literary society Nanka Bungei and of the literary journal of the same name; in 1981 Fujita edited an anthology drawn from the journal, titled Nanka Bungei Senshu, 1965-1980; wrote the first two novels of a projected trilogy: Nochi no kokei (An Agricultural Landscape, 1982) and Tachinoki no kisetsu (An Evacuation Season, 1984).
Additional Biographical Narrative
Fujita Akira [characters], a Kibei-Nisei writer. A native of Brawley, California, Fujita was born February 17, 1920 as the second son of Fujita Keijiro and Kan [characters]. His Japanese immigrant parents originated from Miho [characters] in the city of Shimizu [characters] in Shizuoka Prefecture [characters]. His father was a longtime tenant farmer in the Imperial Valley. In 1922 Fujita was taken to Japan where he was raised in Miho by his maternal grandparents. He attended grammar school in Miho and middle school in Shimizu. In 1937 he matriculated into Waseda University and studied economics, but withdrew from this school in 1940 to return to the United States. Upon his return, he attended high school in Los Angeles, while working as a so-called school boy. Before the outbreak of the Pacific War, he was farming with his father in the Imperial Valley.
During the Second World War, Fujita was successively interned at Poston, Arizona, Tule Lake, California, and Crystal City, Texas. While interned at Tule Lake, he edited a literary journal called Doto [characters]. Seven issues of this journal were issued in 1944 and 1945. Fujita also contributed to the Tessaku [characters], another literary journal published at Tule Lake, also in 1944 and 1945. In 1945 he renounced his American citizenship under duress, and in the following year he was transferred to Crystal City. After his release from this final internment camp, he settled down in Southern California where he worked as a gardener until his retirement. In 1955 he married Grace Yaeno Hironaka [characters], a Kibei. And in 1957 he regained his American citizenship.
In the postwar era, Fujita was the central figure in a Southern California literary society called the Nanka Bungei [characters]. From 1965 to 1985 this society published the Nanka Bungei, a literary journal named after the society. The initial membership of the society consisted primarily of those former Tule Lake internees who had been associated with the Tessaku. In 1981 Fujita edited an anthology of selected writings from the Nanka Bungei published under the title Nanka Bungei Senshu [characters], 1965 - 1980. In the succeeding years, he published his own fictional works, beginning with Nochi no Kokei [characters] in 1982 followed by Tachinoki no Kisetsu [characters] in 1984, the first two novels in a projected trilogy spanning the prewar, wartime, and postwar periods. Unfortunately, he never completed the third volume.
The Akira Fujita papers consist of diaries, 1946, 1978-1989; drafts, galleys, and manuscripts; incoming correspondence files, 1972-1989; personal memorabilia; copies of Fujita's published writings; and books by Nanka Bungei writers and others. The incoming correspondence files include letters from Nanka Bungei writers, members, and associates, 1972-1992, letters from Japanese scholars, writers, and publishers, 1976-1989; letters from Fujita family relatives in Japan, 1971-1987; letters and cards from Fujita family friends, 1972-1986; and miscellaneous letters, 1973 - 1986.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of diaries, manuscripts, drafts, galleys, incoming correspondence files, personal memorabilia, copies of Akira Fujita's published writings, and books by Nanka Bungei writers and others. Incoming correspondence files include letters from Nanka Bungei writers, members, and associates; letters from Japanese scholars, writers and publishers; letters from Fujita family members in Japan; letters and cards from Fujita family friends; and miscellaneous letters.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Diaries: 1946 & 1978-89 (Boxes 1-5).
Manuscripts (Boxes 6-8).
Incoming correspondence files (Boxes 9-16).
Personal memorabilia (Boxes 17-18).
Published works (Boxes 19-25).
Publications of Nanka Bungei writers (Boxes 26-28).
Publications of other writers (Boxes 29-32).
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Japanese American Research Project - Fading Footsteps of the Issei (Collection 2010). Available at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Diaries.; Japanese literature -- California, Southern -- Archives.; American literature -- Japanese American authors -- Archives.; Fujita, Akira, 1920- --Archives.; Nanka Bungei (Literary society)
- Diaries, 1946, 1978-89 (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
  - January 1-February 26, 1946. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - January 1-June 27, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - June 28-December 31, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - January 1-June 11, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - June 12-December 31, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January 1-May 31, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - June 1-November 3, 1980. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - November 4, 1980-April 30, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - May 1-September 14, 1981. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - September 15, 1981-January 17, 1982. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - January 18-April 25, 1982. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - April 26-August 26, 1982. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - August 27, 1982-January 7, 1983. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - January 8-August 31, 1983. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - September 1, 1983-May 21, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - May 22-October 29, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - October 30, 1984-March 18, 1985. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - March 19-November 24, 1985. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - January 1-June 24, 1986. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - June 25-November 30, 1986. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - December 1, 1986-August 1, 1987. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - March 17-November 30, 1988. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - December 1, 1988-December 29, 1989. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Drafts and Galleys (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Drafts of chapters 5 and 6, Nochi no Kokei. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - First galleys, Nochi no Kokei. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Two second galleys, Nochi no Kokei. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Drafts of parts 1 to 4, Tachinoki no Kisetsu. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Drafts of parts 5 to 9, Tachinoki no Kisetsu. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Other drafts, Tachinoki no Kisetsu. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Galleys, Tachinoki no Kisetsu. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Tule Lake Senji Kakurisho [characters]. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous essays, stories, and commentaries. (Box 7, Folder 2 & 3)
  - 3 draft notebooks. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Papers pertaining to the compilation of Nanka Bungei Senshu. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Papers pertaining to the publication of Nochi no Kokei. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of letters. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Nanka Bungei Manuscripts (Box 8)
    - Incomplete draft of Okidokei [characters] by Kagawa Bunichi [characters]. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 2 stories by Mitogawa Mitsuo [characters]. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 5 stories by various writers. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous essays, poems, and commentaries. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Incoming Correspondence Files (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)
  - Nanka Bungei Writers, Members, and Associates (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11)
    - Tomiko Stahl [characters], 1979-1982.; 17 letters (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Tomiko Stahl., 1983-1989.; 20 letters (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Yoshie Stagg [characters], 1978-1981.; 16 letters (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Ao Tokio [characters] (aka So Ryuichi [characters]), 1972-1986.; 13 letters and 2 postcards (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Furuta Soichi [characters], 1979-1990.; 14 letters and 1 postcard. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Shigeko Garcia [characters], 1983-1986.; 9 letters. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Yamashiro Masao [characters], 1974-1985.; 9 letters and 1 postcard. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Norimoto Keizo [characters] (aka Nomoto Ippei [characters]), 1976-1986.; 9 letters. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Karl S. Tsuji (aka Tsuji Akihiko [characters]), 1980-1983.; 6 letters. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Masuda Itsuko [characters] (aka Sonegawa Itsuko [characters]), 1971-1987.; 5 letters (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Karaki Yasko [characters] (aka Karaki Yasue [characters]), 1981-1987.; 5 letters (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Yamazaki Hitomi [characters] (aka Yamazaki Isshin [characters]), 1983-1987.; 5 letters. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Kosaka Miyoko [characters], 1979-1983.; 5 letters. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Tomoko Poquette (aka Kamioka Tomoko [characters]), 1978-1979.; 4 letters. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Yamazaki Jiro [characters], 1980-1983.; 4 letters (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Togawa Akira and Kimi [characters], 1979-1984.; 4 letters (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Kagawa Bunichi and Shizuko [characters], 1978-1984.; 3 letters (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Hiratsuka Unichi [characters], 1981-1985.; 6 letters (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Takemoto Yoshihito [characters], 1979-1989.; 7 letters (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Arthur Iwasaki, 1986-1988.; 6 letters (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Yashima Taro [characters], 1981-1984.; 6 letters (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Maeda Sei [characters], 1979-1981.; 4 letters and 1 postcard (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1974-1982.; 16 letters and 1 postcard (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1983-1992.; 11 letters and 1 postcard (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Japanese Scholars, Writers, and Publishers (Box 12)
    - Ishikawa Yoshimi and Minako [characters], 1981-1987.; 23 letters and 3 postcards (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Tsurutani Hisashi [characters], 1978-1989.; 26 letters and 1 postcard (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Hazumi Eiji [characters], 1977-1989.; 14 letters and 3 postcards (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Ito Kazuo [characters], 1976.; 5 letters (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Murakami Yumiko [characters], 1983-1986.; 3 letters and 1 postcard (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Suzuki Makoto [characters] (Renga Shobo Shinsha [characters]), 1981-1982.; 6 letters (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Yoshimura Chikai [characters] (Heibonsha [characters]), 1983-1988.; 6 letters (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Yatsuhashi Takayuki [characters] (Chunichi Shimbun [characters]), 1980-1982.; 5 letters (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Other scholars, 1976-1988.; 6 letters and 1 postcard (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Relatives in Japan (Box 13)
    - Fujita Namie, Kiyoo, Kazuko, and Akio [characters], 1971-1986.; 26 letters (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Ishino Yuriko, Isao, and Harumi [characters], 1975-1987.; 9 letters (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Omura Kiyoko, Takashi, Midori, and Fumiko [characters], 1978-1981.; 9 letters (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Hirata Michiko and Yumiko [characters], 1980-1984.; 8 letters (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Tsuboi Koichi [characters], 1972-1984.; 8 letters (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Other relatives, 1975-1982.; 3 letters (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Family Friends in America and in Japan (Box 14)
    - Christy and Eric Rosa, 1972-1983.; 24 letters and 1 postcard (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Mimori Robertson, 1983-1989.; 5 letters (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Frank and Frances Shoda, 1979-1980.; 4 letters (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Dai Koichi, Teruko, and Kumie, 1979-1980.; 3 letters and 1 postcard (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Otera Shizuko [characters], 1979-1984.; 4 letters (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Ogawa Masao and Eiko [characters], 1972-1985.; 12 letters (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Kita Yuji, Motoko, Hisako, and Yuko [characters], 1980-1986.; 2 letters and 7 postcards (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Letters and Postcards (Box 15, Box 16)
    - 13 letters and 2 postcards, 1973-1979. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 16 letters, 1980-1981. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 9 letters, 1982. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 11 letters, 1983. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 13 letters, 1984. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 12 letters and 2 postcards, 1985-1986. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - 14 letters, 1987-1989. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 24 letters, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 4 letters, UCLA Library, 1982-1985. (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Personal Memorabilia (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Japanese family registry of the Fujita family. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Fujita Keijiro Japanese passport and wartime identifications. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Papers pertaining to father's funeral, (1948). (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Papers pertaining to wartime internment camps. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Tule Lake internees autograph book. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Papers pertaining to the United States Citizenship Retrieval suit. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Affidavits pertaining to the United States Citizenship Retrieval suit. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence between the Fujitas and Wayne M. Collins, Attorney at Law, 1953-1958. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - 3 English word practice notebooks. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - 4 English word practice notebooks. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Address books and phone books. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Name cards. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Bills and receipts. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Photos and negatives. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous papers. (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Published Works (Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25)
  - Doto, 1944-1945 (Box 19)
    - Vol. 1, July 1944. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 2, August 20, 1944. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 4, November 10, 1944. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Vol. 5, January 20, 1945. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Vol. 6, April 6, 1945. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Collection of prefaces and editorials, Vols. 1-7. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Essays and stories. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Essays, notes, and stories. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Nanka Bungei (Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24)
    - 1965-1969.
      - Vols. 1-2, 1965-1966. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Vols. 3-4, 1966-1967. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Vols. 5-6, 1967-1968. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Vols. 7-8, 1968-1969. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 1969-1973.
      - Vols. 9-10, 1969-1970. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Vols. 11-12, 1970-1971. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Vols. 13-14, 1971-1972. (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Vols. 15-16, 1972-1973. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - 1973-1977.
      - Vols. 17-18, 1973-1974. (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Vols. 19-20, 1974-1975. (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Vols. 21-22, 1975-1976. (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - Vols. 23-24, 1976-1977. (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - 1977-1980.
      - Vols. 25-26, 1977-1978. (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Vols. 27-28, 1978-1979. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Vols. 29-30, 1979-1980. (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - 1981-1986.
      - Vols. 31-32, 1981-1982. (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Vols. 33-34, 1983-1984. (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Vol. 35, 1985. (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Nanka Bungei Tokubetsugo [characters], 1986. (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Books and essays. (Box 25)
    - Nochi no Kokei. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Nanka Bungei Senshu. (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Tachinoki no Kisetsu. (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clippings of essays and commentaries. (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Publications of Nanka Bungei Writers (Box 26, Box 27, Box 28)
  - Kagawa Bunichi, Zuihitsu Wagamishi Hoho [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Kagawa Bunichi, Shishu [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Kagawa Bunichi, Okidokei [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Kagawa Bunichi, Hidden Frame. (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Yamazaki Isshin, Amerika Horo Zakki [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Hagio Imosaku [characters], Imin no Uta [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Togawa Akira, Mitsubachi no Uta [characters]. (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - So Ryuichi, essays and story., 4 items. (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - So Ryuichi, Akishi no Kawa [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Nomoto Ippei, Karifuorunia Orai [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Nomoto Ippei, Amerika Nikkei Kijinden [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Nomoto Ippei, Shihen Danso [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Yashima Taro and Nomoto Ippei, Yakaranda [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Furuta Soichi, A Man Never Becoming a Line. (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Yamashiro Masao, Toi Taigan [characters]. (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings of essays and commentaries by various writers. (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Senryu Tsubame [characters]., 11 items. (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Kodama [characters]., 7 items. (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Karifuorunia Tanka [characters]., 4 items. (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Shigeko Garcia, Kushu Amerika [characters]. (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Yonashiro Seishin [characters], Topazu no Yuyake [characters]. (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Uesu Yoshiko [characters], Remon no Niwa [characters]. (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Shiso no Kagaku [characters]. (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Noda Kasen [characters], incomplete photocopy of Amerika ni Oyu [characters]. (Box 28, Folder 8)
- Publications of Other Writers (Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32)
  - Inoue Yasushi [characters], Wadatsumi Dai-ichibu [characters]. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Inoue Yasushi, Wadatsumi Dai-nibu [characters]. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Inoue Yasushi, Wadatsumi Dai-sanbu [characters]. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Kita Morio [characters], Kagayakeru Aoki Sora no Shitade [characters]. (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Kita Morio, Kagayakeru Aoki Sora no Shitade 2. (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Saotome Mitsugu [characters], Okei [characters], Vols. 1-2. (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Ishikawa Yoshimi, Sutoroberi Boi [characters]. (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Watanabe Kieko [characters], Purumeria no Kokageni [characters]. (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Watanabe Kieko. Tantarasu no Niji [characters]. (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Sanga Moyu [characters], abbreviated version for NHK television drama. (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Tsurutani Hisashi, America-Bound. Translated by Betsy Scheiner. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Tsurutani Hisashi, translator, Amerika Seibu Bungaku [characters]. Originally written by J. K. Folsom.. (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Tsurutani Hisashi, miscellaneous essays and newspaper articles. (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Shirai Noboru [characters], Karifuorunia Nikkeijin Kyosei Shuyojo [characters]. (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Yamaguchi Chiyo and Hideo [characters], Yashi no Hazure [characters]. (Box 32, Folder 5)